Hey everyone, ready for a deep dive? Let's talk about AI, specifically LLMs, those large language
models. We've got a real interesting research paper hot off the press. Title's a bit of a
mouthful though, ready? LLMs know more than they show on the intrinsic representation of LLM
hallucinations. Kitchy, right. But it gets straight to the point, doesn't it? Why do these powerful
LLMs sometimes just make stuff up? That's what we're diving into today. It's like when you ask
an LLM for a simple fact, you know, for work or something, and it gives you something totally
off base, you're just left there thinking, did it? Did it just make that up? Exactly. And this
research team, they didn't just stop at, oops, the AI got it wrong. They actually looked inside
several different LLMs, wanted to see if there was something more going on, something about how these
models understand or maybe misunderstand the whole idea of truth. One thing that really caught my eye
was this whole exact answer token thing. I know we've got some tech savvy listeners, but just in
case, you mind breaking that down for us. Sure, sure. Think of LLMs as being made of these, well,
building blocks of language. They're called tokens, kind of like how we use words, but for these
models. Now, what they found is that some tokens, when the LLM is putting together its response,
they matter more when it comes to whether the model think what it's saying is true. Those are the exact
answer tokens. So it's not just the final answer itself, but these specific tokens inside it that give
us clues about what the LLM is thinking, right? Like, is it sure of itself or is it about to go off the
rails? Exactly. And that's a big deal because you see, a lot of the time people just looked at the
final output, the last token to understand errors. This research says, hold on, there's more to it.
These exact answer tokens, often right in the middle of the response, they're like a much stronger
signal about how confident the model is. It's almost like the LLM is like emphasizing,
maybe even second guessing, the most important part of its answer. Makes you wonder if we could
use this to predict when an LLM is about to have one of those hallucination moments.
That's what the researchers wanted to know. They actually built these little AI detectives,
probing classifiers, to look at the LLM's internal signals at the exact moment it's processing these
exact answer tokens, like trying to read the AI's mind. Okay, hold on. So they built AIs to spy on
other AIs. Wild. But did it work? Could they tell if an LLM was about to give a wrong answer
just by looking at those tokens? It's pretty amazing. But yeah, they were surprisingly accurate.
Way better at predicting those errors than older methods that focused on other things.
So we're talking about a potential breakthrough here, right? By looking at how much emphasis an
LLM puts on certain words, we might be able to tell if we should trust what it's saying. That's huge
for making AI more reliable. It really is. But there's always a but, isn't there? They didn't
stop there. The researchers wanted to know if these AI detectives, these probing classifiers,
could generalize. Could they spot errors across different types of tasks? So if they trained a
probe on, say, trivia questions, would it also catch errors in, I don't know, analyzing a movie review?
Exactly. And this is where things get even more interesting. While the probes did show some
ability to transfer their error spotting skills, it wasn't a perfect system. It seems like different
AI skills, like knowing a fact versus understanding how someone feels, those might rely on different
mechanisms for figuring out truth. So no single lie detector for LLMs, then? Makes sense, I guess.
Our brains are complicated, so why wouldn't these models be the same? But if that's the case,
how do we even begin to understand these different errors, let alone fix them?
Well, the researchers, they really dug into this. They focused on one type of task,
answering trivia questions. But instead of just right or wrong, they came up with this whole system
to categorize errors based on how often the LLM messed up the same question.
So they were looking for patterns, trying to understand the AI's thought process. Like,
okay, sometimes you get this right, sometimes wrong. What's the deal?
Exactly. And they found some interesting things. For example, sometimes the LLM would mostly get an
answer wrong, but then, bam, nail it out of nowhere. That little difference, always wrong versus
sometimes right, could mean completely different things are causing those errors.
That IS wild. Like, the LLM knows the answer somewhere in there, but can't always access it.
It's like when you're taking a test and you know you studied it, but it's just not there. But could the
researchers predict what kind of mistake the LLM would make just by looking at those signals inside?
That just seems next level. You're not going to believe this. They gave it a shot.
Yeah. And the results were pretty impressive. Those error types, those different ways an LLM
can trip up, they are somewhat predictable just by, you know, looking at the model's internal signals.
So we're not just spotting errors anymore. We're figuring out the different kinds of errors.
It's like, instead of just saying the AI messed up, we can say it messed up in this specific way,
and that tells us something. That's huge for AI development, right?
Absolutely. It shows that LLMs aren't just these black boxes spitting out random stuff.
They have systems, intricate ones, for how they think about truth. And those systems work
differently depending on what kind of knowledge or reasoning is involved.
So those systems, they might have different strengths and weaknesses, just like us. Like,
I'm great at facts, but emotions, not so much. Sounds like LLMs could be wired the same way.
That's a great way to put it. And here's where it gets really interesting. They didn't just categorize
the errors. The researchers wanted to use those AI detectives, those probes, to actually
D something about them.
Wait. So instead of just predicting errors, they wanted to see if those probes could actually
help them find the right answers. Like giving the LLM a multiple choice test and the probes
looking at its answers.
You got it. It was like that. They gave the LLM a question multiple times, got a bunch of different
answers. Then they used their probe to choose the answer that seemed most likely to be right,
based on the LLM's internal signals.
So they basically gave the LLM a chance to show its work. Did it work? Did using those signals
actually help them pick better answers?
It did. Using the probe to pick the answer, it consistently led to better accuracy. But here's
the kicker. The improvements were most noticeable when the LLM's internal signals and what it actually
said didn't match up.
You mean when the LLM seemed to know the right answer but still gave the wrong one? Those
always blew my mind.
Exactly those.
Yeah.
The biggest jumps in accuracy came when the LLM was flip-flopping between answers or even
always giving a wrong answer, even though inside it seemed like it knew better.
Like it's second-guessing itself or something? But why would it do that? Seems weird for an AI.
Right. It's a great question. We don't have a perfect answer yet. But this research,
it gives us some possibilities. One idea is maybe it's about confidence or a lack of it.
The LLM sees these hints of the right answer, but it's just not sure enough to commit.
So even though it has an idea of what's right, it doesn't want to bet on it. That's almost human,
isn't it? That hesitation.
It really is. And that's what's so cool about this research. It suggests these AI models,
they're more complex than we think. Of course, it could be other things too. Like maybe it's the
data the LLM was trained on. Ah, right. Those massive data sets full of text, code, all that.
Those data sets, they've got all sorts of human biases in them, don't they?
They do. So even if the LLM's internal signals are saying one thing, the biases from its training
could be pushing it another way. It's like the LLM saying, well, I think this might be right,
but everyone else seems to think it's that. So.
It's going with the crowd, even when it has its own ideas. That's a great analogy. Shows how our
own biases can creep into the AI we build.
And if we don't address those biases. Yeah.
Problems. This is why it's so important, not just to look at what the LLM says, but to understand
how it got there, what's going on inside. If we can read those internal signals better,
we can make AI more accurate, more trustworthy.
It's a whole new way of looking at AI, not just did you get it right, but how did you get there?
What were you thinking? That feels like a game changer.
It really is. And these probing classifiers, they're still new, but they give us a way to do
that, a way to peek inside the AI's brain and start to understand how it makes decisions.
So we went from finding these little clues, these exact answer tokens, to figuring out
different types of errors and maybe even helping LLM's get those answers right more often.
Pretty amazing, right? How fast things are moving.
It really is. But let's talk real world for a sec.
What does this all mean for how we actually use LLM's?
Ah, the big question. I mean, they're everywhere, right? Chatbots, search engines, the works.
But can we really trust them, especially with important stuff like, I don't know, our health,
our money?
Yeah, you don't want your AI financial advisor hallucinating when you're about to retire.
But if this research actually works, if we can make LLM's more reliable, huge potential.
Huge. Imagine AI that's not just helpful, but you can actually depend on it. Accurate info,
real insights, even creative solutions. No more worrying it'll go off on some weird tangent.
Now that's exciting. But how do we get there? What's next? How do we take these research findings
and actually make AI better?
This paper is a great start. It gives us a whole new way to look at LLM errors,
not just surface level, but really getting into how they work on the inside.
No more treating them like a black box, right? We're starting to understand them.
Exactly. And the exciting part is, can we use these internal signals,
these little hints of confidence or doubt, to make their answers more accurate?
So we could actually help them give the right answer even when they're unsure.
Exactly. We might need new ways to train them, maybe even new LLM designs,
ones that make sure their internal signals match what they tell us.
So it's not just about more data, it's about better training,
using what we're learning about how they think.
Right. And as we get better at training, we can build even better probing classifiers.
The ones they use were kind of basic. Imagine what we could do with more powerful tools
to analyze those internal states.
It's like, we're learning to speak their language, not just giving commands,
but having a real dialogue, understanding how they work,
so we can unlock their full potential.
That's what's so cool about this field. It's not just about smart machines,
it's about understanding intelligence itself, theirs, and ours.
Wow. Great point to end on. This deep dive has been amazing.
I'm really seeing LLMs in a new light. We're just at the beginning, aren't we?
Totally. Exciting times for AI. Can't wait to see what's next.
Me too. A huge thank you to our expert for joining us,
for sharing all this incredible knowledge with us.
Happy to be here. Love talking about this stuff.
And to our listeners, thank you here for joining us on this deep dive.
Hope you learned something new and interesting.
Stay curious, everyone, and we'll catch you on the next one.